Finding Aid for Mary M. Culver papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary M. Culver Papers, 1856-2008 1973-1997
Culver, Mary M.
2.3 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
2014064 Aa 2
Papers of Washtenaw County, Mich. architectural historian and preservation activist Mary M. Culver. Collection includes records of Washtenaw County, Mich. historic preservation organizations, Culver's research files and presentations, and images of Michigan historic buildings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Mary M. Culver (donor no. 11082 ) in two different accessions in 2014.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Resident of Ypsilanti, Mich., Mary M. Culver Papers served as member and chair of Ann Arbor's Historic District Commission and other organizations, and taught Michigan architectural history.
Collection reflects Culver's work in the areas of and historic preservation and Michigan architectural history, and divided into two series: Committee Work and Research and Presentations.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Historic Commission (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Architects--Michigan.; Architects and builders--Michigan.; Architecture--Michigan--History.; Historic buildings--Michigan.; Historic districts--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Kimball, Fiske, 1888-1955.; Mills, Stephen, b. 1809.; Pond, Allen Bartlit.; Pond, Irving K. (Irving Kane), 1857-1939.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Color slides.; Photographs.
- Committee work
  The Committee Work series (1 linear foot) includes reports, minutes of meetings, correspondence, proposals, petitions, research materials, and publications of Ann Arbor area historic preservation organizations, most notably, the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission. Issues discussed in documents include surveying buildings and sites of historical and architectural value, preservation of historic buildings and sites, collection and preservation of historic records, establishing Historic Districts with special description and preservation standards, special celebrations and commemorative plaques.
  - Ann Arbor Historical Commission
    - 1959-1967 (Box 1)
      (bound volume)
    - 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Historic District Commission
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1992 (Box 1)
    - Division Street Historic Study Committee, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - Public History Program proposal, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Tomorrow, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
  - Downtown Concept Plan (Draft 2), 1974 (Box 1)
  - Downtown Historic District Study Committee Final report and appendix, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Research and Presentations
  The Research and Presentations series (1.3 linear feet) includes biographies of and Culver's presentations on noted architects and builders with connections to Ann Arbor, Mich. area. Volumes include images of historic buildings by Stephen Mills, Irving Kane Pond, Allen Bartlit Pond, and Fiske Kimball. Also included here are photocopies of Washtenaw County assessment rolls from the 1850s and 1860s and Culver's notebook with description of historic buildings. Visual materials in this series include color slides with images of historic buildings throughout the state (including Ann Arbor, Ypsilanti, Washington, Dundee, Tecumseh, Jackson County, and other areas), photographs of the old Ann Arbor Post Office on Main Street with enclosed National Register of Historic Places Inventory Nomination Form, and slides with miscellaneous images Culver used for teaching.
  - Architectural descriptions, undated (Box 2)
    (notebook)
  - Designers Showcase: a Stephen Mills historic house, 1992, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Greek revival: one pioneer's interpretation of the classical ideal, 1992, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Houses of Stephen Mills by Kevin Coleman, 1991, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Pond & Pond: sons of a pioneer, architects of the U-M's hearthstone, 1995 (?), 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Preservation vanguard: Fiske Kimball: author, architect, and teacher, 1993, 1 volume (Box 2)
    (includes photo slides)
  - Preservation vanguard: Fiske Kimball: author, architect, and teacher, 1994, 1 volume (Box 2)
    (Problems in Architectural Interpretation course)
  - Stephen Mills, 1809 to 1896 his life, his times, and his house, 1991, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Assessment rolls, 1856-1868 (Box 3)
    (outsize)
  - Visual Materials
    - Images of historic buildings (photo slides), 1968-2001, 192 slides (Box 3)
    - Boxed slides, 1990-1997
      - 1324 Pontiac Trail, Ann Arbor, Mich., 59 slides (Box 3)
      - Jackson County, Mich., 54 slides (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous teaching, 53 slides (Box 3)
    - Main Ann Arbor Post Office, 220 Main St., 1976 (photographs and negatives) (Box 3)